<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1"
         xmlns:dc="https://purl.org/dc/terms/"
         xmlns:xsi="https://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
         xmlns:sos="https://sos-search.artdata.slu.se/"
         xmlns:gbif="https://gbif.org/"
         xmlns:snd="https://snd.gu.se/"
         xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 https://rs.gbif.org/schema/eml-gbif-profile/1.1/eml.xsd"
         packageId="33fa6529-cdca-54fe-be80-1095fc2265d3" system="https://sos-search.artdata.slu.se/" scope="system"
         xml:lang="en">
	<dataset>
		<identifier>31ea6c29-adba-64ee-ee81-2341cc2a65b3</identifier>
		<alternateIdentifier>urn:lsid:artdata.slu.se:SOS:Biologg</alternateIdentifier>
		<title>
			Biologg Observations
		</title>
		<publisher>Overstellar Solutions AB</publisher>
		<creator>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Daniel</givenName>
				<surName>Eriksson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<electronicMailAddress>daniel@overstellar.se</electronicMailAddress>
			<organizationName>Overstellar Solutions AB</organizationName>
			<address>
				<city>Enköping</city>
				<country>SE</country>
			</address>
			<onlineUrl>https://www.overstellar.se</onlineUrl>
			<sos:contactNameType>Organizational</sos:contactNameType>
		</creator>
		<metadataProvider>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Daniel</givenName>
				<surName>Eriksson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<electronicMailAddress>daniel@overstellar.se</electronicMailAddress>
			<organizationName>Overstellar Solutions AB</organizationName>
			<address>
				<city>Enköping</city>
				<country>SE</country>
			</address>
			<onlineUrl>https://www.overstellar.se</onlineUrl>
			<sos:contactNameType>Organizational</sos:contactNameType>
		</metadataProvider>
		<pubDate>2021</pubDate>
		<language>ENGLISH</language>
		<licenseName>CC0 1.0</licenseName>
		<abstract>
			<para>Biologg is a mobile application for iOS and Android with the purpose of encouraging citizens to learn about nature by collecting observations of species that they find in nature.
				The app uses gamification to encourage users by, for example, earning credits, and using rewards and challenges.
				These gamification techniques are used to encourage the users to collect specific species by giving instructions for what to look for.
			</para>
			<para>The app displays species names and taxonomic relationships using the Dyntaxa - Swedish Taxonomic Database maintained at SLU Swedish Species Information Centre.
				The app also displays facts and images of species in Sweden using open data from SLU Swedish Species Information Centre as well as Wikipedia.
			</para>
			<para>The app has no automatic function for suggesting identification of species (such as image recognition) but users can help each other by suggesting species identity or confirming species identification.
				Users can also report other users' observation records if they are incorrect or violating the app's terms and conditions.
			</para>
			<para>Each observation record includes one or more photographic images, a species identification, time and GPS position.
				When a new observation is recorded the time and location are fetched automatically, but users can modify the information in cases when no data are fetched or if the fetched data appear incorrect.
				An observation can be recorded at species level, or at a higher taxonomic level. Users can also choose to record an observation as "identified with uncertainty" when they are not certain that their species identification is correct.
				Images are mandatory, that is only observations with images are recorded, and can be used to verify the record.
			</para>
			<para>
				The app is developed and managed by the software company Overstellar Solutions AB.
			</para>
		</abstract>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>Occurrence</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Type Vocabulary: https://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_type.xml</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<keywordSet>
			<keyword>Observation</keyword>
			<keywordThesaurus>GBIF Dataset Subtype Vocabulary: https://rs.gbif.org/vocabulary/gbif/dataset_subtype.xml</keywordThesaurus>
		</keywordSet>
		<intellectualRights>
			<para>
				To the extent possible under law, the publisher has waived all rights to these data and has dedicated them to the <ulink url="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/legalcode">
					<citetitle>Public Domain (CC0 1.0)</citetitle>
				</ulink>. Users may copy, modify, distribute and use the work, including for commercial purposes, without restriction.
			</para>
		</intellectualRights>
		<coverage>
			<geographicCoverage>
				<geographicDescription>This resource covers Sweden.</geographicDescription>
				<boundingCoordinates>
					<westBoundingCoordinate>10.13</westBoundingCoordinate>
					<eastBoundingCoordinate>24.59</eastBoundingCoordinate>
					<northBoundingCoordinate>69.3</northBoundingCoordinate>
					<southBoundingCoordinate>55.11</southBoundingCoordinate>
				</boundingCoordinates>
			</geographicCoverage>
			<temporalCoverage>
				<sos:TemporalCoverageType>date range</sos:TemporalCoverageType>
				<sos:LivingTimePeriod>NA</sos:LivingTimePeriod>
				<sos:StartDate>2019</sos:StartDate>
				<sos:EndDate>current</sos:EndDate>
			</temporalCoverage>
			<taxonomicCoverage>
				<sos:TaxonomicDescription>All taxa occuring in Sweden.</sos:TaxonomicDescription>
				<taxonId></taxonId>
				<sos:scientificName>Biota</sos:scientificName>
				<sos:TaxonList></sos:TaxonList>
			</taxonomicCoverage>
		</coverage>
		<maintenance>
			<description>
				<para/>
			</description>
			<maintenanceUpdateFrequency>unkown</maintenanceUpdateFrequency>
		</maintenance>
		<contact>
			<individualName>
				<givenName>Daniel</givenName>
				<surName>Eriksson</surName>
			</individualName>
			<electronicMailAddress>daniel@overstellar.se</electronicMailAddress>
			<organizationName>Overstellar Solutions AB</organizationName>
			<address>
				<city>Enköping</city>
				<country>SE</country>
			</address>
			<onlineUrl>https://www.overstellar.se</onlineUrl>
			<sos:contactNameType>Organizational</sos:contactNameType>
		</contact>
		<sos:resourceType>occurence data</sos:resourceType>
		<gbif:resourceSubtype>observation</gbif:resourceSubtype>
		<sos:dataAccessibilityLevel>open</sos:dataAccessibilityLevel>
		<sos:datsetSubtype>opportunistic data</sos:datsetSubtype>
		<sos:resourceHomepage>https://www.biologg.se/</sos:resourceHomepage>
		<gbif:MetadataLanguage>ENGLISH</gbif:MetadataLanguage>
		<gbif:UpdateFrequency>daily</gbif:UpdateFrequency>
		<sos:UpdateFrequencySOS>daily</sos:UpdateFrequencySOS>
		<project>
			<sos:projectTitle></sos:projectTitle>
			<funding>
				Vinnova grant "Allmänheten och naturvård: Biologg, medborgarforskning och biologisk mångfald" supported the project during November 2020 - December 2021.
			</funding>
			<funderName>
				Vinnova
			</funderName>
			<funderIdentifier></funderIdentifier>
			<dc:funderIdentifierType></dc:funderIdentifierType>
			<designDescription></designDescription>
		</project>
		<samplingMethods>
			<studyExtent></studyExtent>
			<samplingDescription>
				Observations of species are collected in an opportunistic manner, i.e. that sampling is at the will of the observer who decides about what, where and when to record.
				Sampling is determined by the activity and behavioural patterns and preferences  of the observers, and may be guided by gamification.
				The inventory type can be described as completely open and opportunistic search, or as guided by gamification.

				Sampling may differ between "projects" i.e. observations collected linked to a specific challenge or other gamification.

				Sampling effort, i.e. the time spent searching and area covered during the search varies and is unknown (no information about sampling effort available).
			</samplingDescription>
			<methodStep>
				No specific procedures or protocols. Sampling is either completely at the will of the observer, or guided by gamification where "games" (e.g. challenge) may give instructions for what to look for, where and/or when.

				Observations are recorded using a mobile app; the device's applications are used to retrieve GPS position and coordinate uncertainty, photographic images, and time.
				The mobile app sources information about taxonomic names and relationships, facts and images for species from external sources.

				A record is produced when an observer searches for an organism, uses the mobile app to identify the species and select a taxon for the record, to take one or more photographic images,
				and to record the observation including the time and the GPS coordinates as set by the device. Only taxa included in SLU Species Information Centre's Dyntaxa database can be selected for the record.

				Records can then be viewed by other users who can review the species or taxon identification, and may suggest a different species identity or confirm species identification.
				The observer who reported the observation receives a notification about other users' suggestions and can choose to accept or reject the suggestion.
				Species suggestions or confirmations are stored in the database, linked to the observation record, and stored in the history of the record.
				When a suggested species (taxon) identification is accepted then the record is updated by changing the taxon for the observation in the database.

				Users can also report other users' observation records as incorrect or if they are violating the app's terms and conditions. Those reports are stored in the original database but can be viewed only by Overstellar Solutions AB.
				Those reports are reviewed and when the record is deemed incorrect or violating the app's terms and conditions then the record is removed from the database.
				The information about species suggestions or confirmations, and other users' reports are currently not included in this data resource.

				All records are stored in the original database but included in this resource only if they include valid geographic coordinates that fall within Sweden's administrative borders.

				The observation records may include observations classed as sensitive according to the list of sensitive species in Sweden (https://doi.org/10.15468/jwbtsb) managed and maintained by SLU Species Information Centre. 
				Those records are kept in their original form in the original database but in this resource shown generalised according to rules used by SLU Species Information Centre.
			</methodStep>
			<qualityControl>
				At present there is no automated quality control of the records.

				There is a user community review process for species identification. Other users can suggest a different species identity or confirming species identification.
				The observer who reported the observation receives a notification about other users' suggestions and can choose to accept or reject the suggestion.
				Other users can also report observation records as incorrect or violating the app's terms and conditions.
				Those reports are reviewed by Overstellar Solutions AB and may be removed when the record is indeed deemed to be incorrect or violating the app's terms and conditions.

				All records are stored in the original database but included in this resource only if they include valid geographic coordinates that fall within Sweden's administrative borders, and a valid time.
			</qualityControl>
		</samplingMethods>
		<additionalMetadata>
			<metadata>
				<gettingStarted></gettingStarted>
				<purpose>
					Biologg is an app with the main purpose of encouraging users to learn more about nature. Users are free to record any kind of observations of species as long as they are wild species that can be found in Sweden. 
					Users are also actively encouraged to record specific species through various challenges that are presented in the app. This is so far mainly to educate the users on what kind of species they can look for, 
					but could in the future also be done in collaboration with partners who are interested in specific data.
				</purpose>
				<sos:personalData></sos:personalData>
				<sos:sensitiveData>yes</sos:sensitiveData>
				<sos:sensitiveDataDescription>
					The observation records may include observations classed as sensitive according the list of sensitive species in Sweden (https://doi.org/10.15468/jwbtsb) managed and maintained by SLU Species Information Centre. 
					Those records are kept in their original form in the original database but in this resource shown generalised according to rules used by SLU Species Information Centre.
				</sos:sensitiveDataDescription>
				<snd:dataFormat></snd:dataFormat>
				<dc:relationType></dc:relationType>
			</metadata>
		</additionalMetadata>
		<citations>
			<sos:resourceCitation>
				Eriksson D, Bergkvist A-K (2021). Biologg Observations. Version X.X. Overstellar Solutions AB. Occurrence dataset.
			</sos:resourceCitation>
		</citations>
	</dataset>
</eml:eml>
